<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dat K Nguyen</title><link href="https://pymalchik.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://pymalchik.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://pymalchik.com/</id><updated>2020-01-09T20:13:00+00:00</updated><subtitle>micro pessimist, macro optimist</subtitle><entry><title>Russianizing Philip Larkin</title><link href="https://pymalchik.com/2020/01/09/russianizing-philip-larkin/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-09T20:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-09T20:13:00+00:00</updated><author><name>datnguyen</name></author><id>tag:pymalchik.com,2020-01-09:/2020/01/09/russianizing-philip-larkin/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A surprisingly under-translated and under-appreciated poet in the Russian literary tradition, yet his voice—cynical, sarcastic, preoccupied with mortality, comfortable with the usage of slang, jargon and cussing within traditional forms—should yield itself well to the Russian language. Or so goes the belief behind this work-in-progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="[https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/48410/days-56d229a0c0c33](https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/48410/days-56d229a0c0c33)"&gt;Days&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Дни&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;В чем смысл дней?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Тех дней, где мы живем.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Грядут да пробуждают&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Вновь и вновь.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Они задуманы для счастья:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Где жить нам, коль не в днях?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ах, тот вопрос решить&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Священник с доктором&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;В шинелях дружно&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Бегут через поля.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="[https://allpoetry.com/Talking-In-Bed](https://allpoetry.com/Talking-In-Bed)"&gt;Talking In Bed&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Разговор в постели&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;В постели лёжа, говорить вдвоём&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Должно быть исключительно легко:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Знак откровенности о ней, о нём.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Но в тишине часы текут, пока&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Снаружи ветер буйный движет, вьёт,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Не прекращая, в небе облака.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;И горизонт—громада темных зданий.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Всё равнодушно к нам. Неясно, как,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;От одиночества на расстоянии&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Предельном, тяжелей найти слова&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Одновременно правды и добра,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Отнюдь ещё не лжи, ещё не зла.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="[https://allpoetry.com/A-Study-Of-Reading-Habits](https://allpoetry.com/A-Study-Of-Reading-Habits)"&gt;A Study of Reading Habits&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Исследуя читательские повадки&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;В книгах  невзгоды лечив,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Дерзкий я баламут,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Портил ночью глаза,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Представляя, как крут,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;С правой задире втащив&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Больше в два раза меня.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Позже, в толстой оправе&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;В зле я увидел прикол.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Облик вампира приняв,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Чинно влача свой подол,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Тешился в женщин ораве,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Пачками их совращав.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ныне чтенье уныло:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Чел, чью рыцарь спёр леди,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Тип, что трусливый тюфяк,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Всё—знакомые бредни.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;От бухла б хоть накрыло,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Книжки—отборнейший шлак.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="translations"></category><category term="poetry"></category><category term="literature"></category></entry><entry><title>On Earth I was briefly reading</title><link href="https://pymalchik.com/2019/12/23/books-2019/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-23T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-23T20:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>datnguyen</name></author><id>tag:pymalchik.com,2019-12-23:/2019/12/23/books-2019/</id><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a man’s character is his fate, says Heraclitus, and in the end there isn’t any way to disguise the nature of the knocks by acoustical work on the door or gloving the knuckles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saul Bellow, The Adventures of Augie March&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Screwtape_Letters"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Screwtape Letters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by C. S. Lewis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lost Letter XXXII&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Dearest Wormwood, My Pigsnie,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Hell, you must gather the remains of your devilish pride, for if you continue your sorry attempts at eliciting compassion we shall suspect you of sympathy for the Enemy. By now you should have learned compassion is an emotion squarely reserved for his domain. Here we go by the currency of stripped-down merit, success at all cost, individualistic conquest of the soul. On that account, you deserve your despondency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One soul slipped through your fingers, yet you must not succumb to the sad state of defeat; observe in the teetering world of man a galore of tempting opportunities to lend it a gentle push into the silent, quotidian abyss. As I walked the bustling squares of London Victoria I could not help feeling invigorated by the realisation of how the passage of time appears to present us with patients of ever-growing promise. Educated men there, mostly, in some rare cases their reason already awoken — I even saw one reading &lt;em&gt;A Grief Observed &lt;/em&gt;on a bench in the park. You may recall the difficulty of engaging in combat directly on the battlefield of ideas. Despair not — when the Enemy closes a door, Our Father Below opens a gutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the efforts of our Philological Arm, achievements of the Enlightenment have soundly come to represent the sovereignty and might of human reason (any connection with the light the Enemy has given them never to be mentioned). In this lies our possibility, for if there exists a swifter path to corruption than through arrogance, we have surely not invented it yet. Do not be discouraged, then, by their confrontation with religious questions of the most complex kind, for in their limits they will manage to derive their independence from the Enemy (at any rate, due to the progress we have made on connectivity and social media, the condition of late modernity is that of a village under carpet bombing; he may not reach the end of one inquiry before another arrives to seize his attention).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take, for instance, the problem of pain. They survey the unjustly afflicted and ponder, how could an all-powerful, benevolent being allow it? There is no rational answer which will satisfy them: that suffering, where not envisioned by our High Command, exists so that goodness, unencumbered by the pursuit of salvation, could be genuine; that it follows from their free will; that through this vehicle the Enemy, who, much to our annoyance, once embodied their pain, opens their ears. Our task is not to locate it (in frankness, I find on occasions astounding the cruelty with which the Enemy expresses his love). Ours is to attach the weights of self-sufficiency to their ankles each time they are about to make a leap of faith. If they believe their inability to glimpse into the Enemy’s designs implies a cosmic void, our work is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once had a patient disintegrating precisely in this manner. A conventionally accomplished man, he thought he was promoting virtue by intermittent church visits, where he did not participate in the community, and mulling over the doctrines. Unable to determine the locus of life’s meaning, he concluded there must have been none, and the world had been ‘empty’, no one but him, aimlessly rolling a boulder up a hill, to fill it. After that, he became a sitting duck. All I needed to do was whisper into his mind, gripped by the melody of its own accord, ‘a working hypothesis’, and, lo and behold, that is what the Enemy was transformed into, his potential reduced to a mere necessity (‘il faudrait l’inventer’, in the pompous locution of their philosopher Voltaire). His arrogance, of course, could not accept a coping mechanism on faith: he pronounced rationality like a holy word and carried it like a badge of honor, his chest bulging forward, straight into Our Father’s house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you see my point? The oyster is full of pearls, and their splendour only eases their abduction. Even as the howl of your failure reverberates through all the levels of the Kingdom of Noise, do not be crippled by it. Those who are tormented shall offer torment in return. And if your next patient is eaten up inside by a hundred indecisions, a hundred visions and revisions, all the better. Let him postulate questions and, unable to resolve them, decide his religion was the misstep of a fool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your affectionate uncle,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Screwtape&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Possessed-Adventures-Russian-Books-People/dp/1847083145"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Possessed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Adventures With Russian Books And The People Who Read Them by Elif Batuman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that cold winter day her veins were bulging on her hands more visibly than usual. She wore a chunky rollneck sweater the colour of her skin, the rosy white about to blend into whiteness of the snow outside. Her veins pulsating like bubbling currents interspersing frozen banks, a sign of life amidst the paling slumber. She was reading from &lt;a href="https://www.poemhunter.com/poem/i-go-out-on-the-road-alone/"&gt;Lermontov&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Выхожу один я на дорогу; / Сквозь туман кремнистый путь блестит. / Ночь тиха. Пустыня внемлет Богу, / И звезда с звездою говорит&lt;/em&gt;. Clawing invisible spheres, she bent her fingers and drew her palms together, as if connecting some distant, mysterious worlds. She repeated the last line from that stanza, &lt;em&gt;And star with star converses,&lt;/em&gt; and looked at me. ‘Isn’t it beautiful?’* *she asked, striking a ceremonial note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elif Batuman, following her own encounters with Russianness, would not have been taken aback by this intense earnestness. At every turn along her journey, it seemed she had been met with oddities of the distinctly Russian kind. There was ‘a dinner from Dostoyevsky’, where one Isaac Babel scholar farcically confronted another (‘IS IT TRUE THAT YOU DESPISE ME?’); her luggage was lost but helpfully Aeroflot provided existential guidance with ‘our Russian phrase &lt;em&gt;resignation of the soul&lt;/em&gt;’; there were unsolvable architectural puzzles (‘The [St Petersburg] ice palace had no clear purpose, but many unclear purposes’); and, of course, overwhelming connotations of mortality: ‘And still life goes on in Chekhov’s garden, where it’s always a fine day for hanging yourself, and somebody somewhere is playing the guitar.’ A New Yorker, she mines this quirkiness for comedy, the Woody Allen brand of funny, in her memoir-cum-love-letter to Russian literature, where these motifs prevail — life uncannily imitating art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crust of her endeavour is revealed when her tone drops the mask of irony and sips into the sentimental; she channels a contagious passion for reading (above, even, creative writing): ‘I stopped believing that … it was possible to compromise something you loved by studying it … Was love really such a tenuous thing? Wasn’t the point of love that it made you want to learn more, to immerse yourself, to become possessed?’ Her personal story is that of choosing to pursue literary criticism, hoping to understand what &lt;em&gt;Anna Karenina&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Eugene Onegin&lt;/em&gt; sought to say, as opposed to learning to write cliché stories in MFA workshops of ‘middle-class women struggling with kleptomania’ and ‘rueful writerly types’. A witty, touching testament to the power of Russian literature — its preoccupation with interior worlds (Chekhov’s ‘two lives’) combined with its lyrical expansiveness, its grand project of rendering ‘comprehensible different kinds of unhappiness’ — to alter the course and attitude of one’s living, Batuman’s book reminded me of how much it had enriched mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fixated on the trembling window. The snow kept falling, its somnambulant rhythm unperturbed by a boy’s awakening. Why would it have been? Nature by itself moved and meant nothing; it required an observer — a reader — to imbue the deadening frost of the everyday with sacramental, like stars needed stargazers to be heard &lt;em&gt;conversing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those lines from Mayakovsky: &lt;em&gt;if stars are lit / it means — there is someone who needs it. / It means — someone wants them to be, / that someone deems those specks of spit / magnificent&lt;/em&gt;. It meant someone was noticing. That’s what reading was to my teacher and that’s the literature Russians imparted on me: the art of stargazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On_Earth_We%27re_Briefly_Gorgeous"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Earth We’re Briefly Gorgeous&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Ocean Vuong&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me begin again. Ma, I used to wonder what a tale of Vietnamese immigration might look like. I didn’t know if any existed, but I sensed it had to be a book of searing honesty, of bold, uncompromising ambition — to render poetry of yellow bodies. If it did not, I thought a man of singular talent had to wrench it into being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How I would sit in a cafe trying to express what its existence meant. That it would scour all that we had known, in our blood, bones and flesh. How it would enter nail salons and tell of its back rooms where ‘our women squat on the floor over huge woks that pop and sizzle over electric burners, cauldrons of pho simmer and steam up the cramped spaces’. How it would transport me back to rows and rows of big-box bazaar containers, enclosing dreams projected onto counterfeit goods, doors creaking every sunrise with aspirations of migrants, shells rusting away with undocumented desperation, in their stern quiescence presiding, like some immovable dictator, over plights of our people, mouths parched by indifferent suns, persistently mustering — ‘because the mouth must eat’ — a handful foreign phrases that they knew. The life from which you saved me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In principle, in tone, in subject matter — painfully intimate yet politically subversive, aware that for people like us it is one and the same, that the quest for affection and the quest for achievement are subsumed into an act of rebellion. How it would set that scene: a child translating for a parent by the butcher counter, her body twisting, turning, twirling, mooing, compressing its humanity into a semblance of cattle — its only path to understanding — all to buy oxtail, all to make bún bò huế, all to be met with white teeth of roaring amusement. A trivial matter sowing the seed of spokesman’s burden: though half-confused, he learns about the gift of language — to tell the stories of the speechless. That voice, once more, would ring inside me, one from across a tottering wooden table, edges peeling off, in an office with ragged wallpaper, as I asked for another parent’s son or daughter to be accepted into school, ‘I never thought a Vietnamese boy could speak our language so well.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language — the edifice upholding our expectations, our struggles, our triumphs; not the dress of thought but the thought itself. How acutely, like strangers in a foreign land — what you always said we were — he would be attuned to it, how we cloak our selves in the texture of our words and are shaped by their garments. How we have the same one, in Vietnamese, for missing and remembering: nhớ. The gift of memory equates for us, then, to the curse of longing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma, what I’m trying to say is that I’ve read Roland Barthes’ &lt;em&gt;A Lover’s Discourse &lt;/em&gt;but still instinctively congeal when I want to utter “I love you”. In other words, in some important sense my education remains precariously incomplete, my loving — a clumsy, suffocating lump in my throat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A part of me keeps wishing to not so much say as feel these thoughts in Vietnamese, but any meaningful attempt bears witness to ruins, that is, the distance between you and me. That book would walk it: &lt;em&gt;‘&lt;/em&gt;Our mother tongue, then, is, no mother at all — but an orphan.’ An orphan, Ma — is that how we should call that immigrant ailment, that yearning for what was never known but is irrevocably lost?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma, maybe poetry makes nothing happen but through this book I would relive a Joseph Brodsky verse, of ‘homeland’ which, by the grace of a poet, ‘Obtained the gift of speech in deaf-mute space ocean&lt;em&gt;.’ &lt;/em&gt;The time when I boyishly believed that writing survived by this universal hope. &lt;em&gt;‘&lt;/em&gt;The truest ruins are not written down&lt;em&gt;’&lt;/em&gt;, it would say, aware of how literature enlists those doomed idealists, armed with nothing but tender songs of their own ordinariness, bent on preserving life against the conquest of the steadily ticking ravager of bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope — a mother’s hope that her son would amount to something. ‘If we are lucky, the end of the sentence is where we might begin.’ That man would get his name in hope that an ocean could connect countries. Through him, they would have spoken to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seize_the_Day_(novel)"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seize the Day&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herzog_(novel)"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Herzog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Saul Bellow&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Mr Bellow,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You have drawn my attention to the problem of, if I may say so, weasels in distress. Of financial markets you wrote, ‘they haven’t got the genuine courage to kill, and they erect a symbol of it. The money.’ On the first part, I concur. On the second, I have my doubts. We were too exhausted to erect much of anything.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It was Erich Fromm (1900–1980) who posited the shakiness of man’s self-esteem if judged by the merits of competition, the validation famine. But according to René Girard’s (1923–2015) mimetic theory, destructive competition for prestige is inescapable, part of the human condition. Give this man Wilhelm all the riches in the world and he will still be unhappy. Tears or not, an obsession must be transcended, spiritually cleansed — there you have me, somewhat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But what did you mean to show with Moses Elkanah Herzog? The impotence of intellect before the crumbling of the heart? Professor Herzog fell for that old Schopenhauerian fallacy of curing desire with the pursuit of knowledge… To think that the prison of the mind could liberate! Men, failing to oppress women, oppress themselves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For instance? Well, for instance, what it means to be a man. And what else was it? ‘In a society that was no community and devalued the person. Owing to the multiplied power of numbers which made the self negligible.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The negligible self! I, too, have vehemently dreamed up Madeleines — in every smile, the foreboding. Le cœur en montagne russe. Didn’t she warn him? ‘Anyway, it’ll never be boring.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And yet? An epic conception of human existence must not permanently rely on the crutches of misery lest it detract from its own grandeur. Every weasel, no matter how smart and vain, arrives at the same prescription: venture outwards. Live your wild and precious life.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Moral_Animal"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Moral Animal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Robert Wright and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On_Human_Nature"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Human Nature&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by EO Wilson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it was my life story that made me stand on the nurture side of the eternal debate. Perhaps the Existentialists and the Stoics convinced me of man’s ultimate freedom. People are near-infinitely malleable owners of their destiny, I wanted to believe, and culture, not genes, plays the crucial role in who they become. An introduction to evolutionary psychology scribbled a giant question mark on top of all that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;On Human Nature&lt;/em&gt;, EO Wilson put forth a controversial but truly compelling case against the tabula rasa theory of the brain. Yes, humans can learn — and Wilson stresses the interplay between cultural environment and hereditary predisposition — but at best we are learning machines pre-trained on the data from tens of thousands of years ago. What we can learn is highly constrained. The outcomes are far from being uniformly likely. And we have much more in common with ants than we’ve been willing to accept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with the premise: all living organisms evolved through natural selection and exist for no other purpose than genetic survival. Human traits and behaviour, therefore, emerged in their current form in the process of adaptation: these are the traits and behaviours which maximised reproductive success, at least in hunter-gatherer societies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so good. Is biological origin of mankind such a shocker? But as one reads, a barrage of blows awaits an unprepared psyche. ‘Morality performs no other demonstrable function’, Wilson writes, than to keep ‘human genetical material … intact.’ ‘The genes hold culture on a leash’, he ensues. The itch of curiosity forces one to ask, well, how long is the leash? ‘Long,’ replies Wilson, but that is plainly unsatisfactory. &lt;em&gt;How much&lt;/em&gt; is attributable to natural selection? Could some traits be accidental mutations &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spandrel_(biology)"&gt;of no value&lt;/a&gt; to genetic fitness? Say, what is the reproductive strategy behind the love of letters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jury is still out, and the verdict depends on your degree of “&lt;a href="https://www.nybooks.com/articles/1997/06/12/darwinian-fundamentalism/"&gt;Darwinian&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.nybooks.com/articles/1997/10/09/evolutionary-psychology-an-exchange/"&gt;fundamentalism&lt;/a&gt;”. Some indeed espouse the all-encompassing view of adaptation&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;Cynical? Wait for it: the brain may have evolved to think that. If we deeply believed in our goodness, we’d find it easier to cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Moral Animal&lt;/em&gt; by Robert Wright is a great overview of these ideas. Wright touches on the evolutionary roots of a diverse range of phenomena from mating (biologists have fun naming a mental mechanism the &lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1037/gpr0000022"&gt;mate ejection module)&lt;/a&gt; to an innate sense of injustice. It illustrates Darwinian theories on the life story of Darwin, interesting in its own right (did you ever think of nice guy Darwin as an alpha male?). Perhaps most importantly, the book aims to maintain integrity and discusses the strength of evidence for its propositions. It would be an understatement to say that evolutionary psychology may stand on shaky empirical ground. By its nature, it doesn’t easily lend itself to rigorous empirical methods and invites “&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03014-4?fbclid=IwAR2btb7L-0W9imDhws_kX7ZXoMDzz9HP6qGkgutw7hBi0CDV-2nS5N_uAC8"&gt;scientism”&lt;/a&gt; to defend dubious behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, its intellectual progeny belongs to a rare breed, the Pandora’s box of ideas: once encountered, they cannot be blissfully swept under the rug of the quotidian. Enveloping sensations they enter the mind and demand to be wrestled with. Standing atop the cathedral of scientific materialism, clasped by as human a need as any, Wright and Wilson meditate on the ethical consequences of Darwinism. After all, natural selection is a value-free process and so does not enforce normative directives. Just because something is “natural” does not mean it is “right”. After the “what”, they thus attempt to infer the “so what”. That, of course, assumes a generous amount of free will on our part, but it’s an engrossing exercise nonetheless. Then again, maybe my brain was programmed to enjoy that sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1936/1*xG5xtOsyyGBdXZmVg4yYUw.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category><category term="culture"></category><category term="literature"></category></entry><entry><title>2018: A reading list of my own</title><link href="https://pymalchik.com/2018/01/01/books-2018/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-01T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T20:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>datnguyen</name></author><id>tag:pymalchik.com,2018-01-01:/2018/01/01/books-2018/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the rewards of being outside a formal education system is the greater freedom to get lost in the labyrinth of your own passions, accidental findings and mishaps. Here’s my attempt at following 2018’s ball of thread to some kind of sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Siddhartha by Hermann Hesse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What could I say to you that would be of value, except that perhaps you seek too much, that as a result of your seeking you cannot find.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite read of 2018. Yearning to understand himself and the meaning of life (aka “enlightenment”), Siddhartha ventures into the world and travels many roads: that of an ascetic; a rich businessman and a sensual lover; an isolated but contented ferryman. He never quite finds transcendence in any one of these roles, and yet discovers it in the totality of his life. Through its deceptively simple prose &lt;em&gt;Siddhartha&lt;/em&gt; evokes a powerful idea, that life cannot be understood through egghead pondering alone. It has to be lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civilization by Kenneth Clark&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book I recommended the most to my friends in 2018 (Full disclosure: I found out about it through Paul Graham’s website), &lt;em&gt;Civilization&lt;/em&gt; is a history of the Western world from around the Dark Ages onwards as told through its art. It leaves you with a feeling not dissimilar to an engrossing museum tour — as I have already waxed lyrical in my goodreads &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2239940817?book_show_action=false&amp;amp;from_review_page=1"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Make Friends and Influence People by Dale Carnegie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those books that can easily attract skeptical glances on the tube, &lt;em&gt;How to Make Friends &lt;/em&gt;does give cliched advice on dealing with people: praise often, listen intently, take an interest. I heard its teachings were considered manipulative, but reading it left me with an impression of the opposite: Dale Carnegie insists that a kind predisposition towards other people cannot be faked. It ultimately reminded me of a Warren Buffet quote, &lt;em&gt;“The only way to get love is to be lovable.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Courage to be Disliked by Fumitake Koga and Ichiro Kishimi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book introduced me to Adlerian psychology, of which I knew practically nothing, and upon completing it I couldn’t help but think of its similarities to stoic philosophy (then again, I find its traces in many self-help books…): its emphasis on personal responsibility, capacity for change and free will, and its attribution of psychological problems to our constant worrying about the things we do not control. The authors claim that the book takes the form of a Socratic dialogue between a “philosopher” and a “youth”, though I cannot recall if Socrates was ever questioned by a petulant teenager…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swann’s Way by Marcel Proust&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great whales of literature (and this is just its first volume…), it proved as intimidating and awe-inspiring in its display of linguistic craftsmanship as I thought it would be. The number of asides and philosophical musings triggered by seemingly mundane details is mind-boggling, but it is also great entertainment–I particularly enjoyed &lt;em&gt;Swann in Love&lt;/em&gt;: it features probably my favorite passages about the torments of jealousy that can befall an infatuated mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sympathizer by Viet Thanh Nguyen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Remember, you’re not half of anything, you’re twice of everything.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times laugh-out-loud funny and at times heartbreaking, this is my new all-time favorite. It is an immigrant novel (in the form of a spy thriller), exploring, as you may expect, issues of displacement, belonging and identity — but what I especially love about it is that the narrative does not drown in self-indulgence. It is clearly personal, and yet there is a huge amount of historical research, especially on Hollywood’s depiction of the Vietnam War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Google Works by Eric Schmidt and Jonathan Rosenberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things written or said by Eric Schmidt have persistently been on my mind this year. First, on a &lt;a href="https://mastersofscale.com/eric-schmidt-innovation-managed-chaos/"&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; with Reid Hoffman, he mentioned how &lt;em&gt;flying&lt;/em&gt; helped him improve his decision-making, inspiring me to try it out for myself (work in progress). Second, in &lt;em&gt;How Google Works&lt;/em&gt; he wrote “Hiring is the most important thing you do”, and this has echoed in my mind long after I put this book down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dealers of Lightning: Xerox PARC and the Dawn of the Computer Age by Michael A. Hiltzik&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fascinating account of the personalities, work practices and office culture that gave the world, among many other innovations, the first PC and the laser printer. I was amused to find that PARC ran a weekly discussion club akin to a seminar, called &lt;em&gt;Beat the Dealer&lt;/em&gt;, where researchers could present a topic of their liking and–on most occasions–tear apart each other’s ideas, without ever getting personal. A practice I have become partial to in my own career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicomachean Ethics by Aristotle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Intellect itself, however, moves nothing, but only the intellect which aims at an end and is practical”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man obtains happiness, Aristotle argues, through living virtuously, morally and intellectually, and Aristotle discusses at length the virtuous ideals such as courage, justice, “temperance” and practical wisdom. You constantly find here the idea of the “golden middle”, that moral virtues are the mean between two extremes (like courage is the mean between cowardice and rashness). Considering how much of Western ethics supposedly descends from Aristotle, this was an elucidating book which demanded patience and persistence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roma by Alfonso Cuaron&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roma is the most beautiful and poignant movie I’ve seen in 2018 (not that I’ve seen many). Filmed in black and white, it features stunning cinematography and incredible sound (the most beautiful sound of waves!): reminiscing, I feel like every shot and every scene were cinematographic poetry. It is a moving tribute to the sacrifices women can make to raise us, and during the screening I caught myself thinking about how unmanly (whatever that means…) men can be in a society fuelled by machismo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Golden Hour by Kacey Musgraves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven’t stumbled on an album in 2018 that I loved as much as &lt;em&gt;A Deeper Understanding&lt;/em&gt; by The War on Drugs or &lt;em&gt;Ctrl&lt;/em&gt; by SZA in the previous year, but I really liked &lt;em&gt;Golden Hour&lt;/em&gt;. Uplifting, twisting disco and autotune with country, the best thing about it is its earnestness–it is absolutely disarming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out my &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/4672749?shelf=to-read"&gt;reading list&lt;/a&gt; for 2019 (and, most likely, beyond)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category><category term="culture"></category><category term="literature"></category></entry></feed>